After you are done with the install
you can find a new group [Git] in a start menu.
[Git Bash] and [Git CMD] - these are the command line interface shells to work with git.
Git Bash is a port of unix bash version. Git CMD is a usual windows cmd.
And finally this [Git GUI] is a simple UI.
Command line will be our main tool because,
it gives access to all the power of git.
Once you master a command line you will figure out UI easilly,
this or any other one.
We could have chosed this one [Git CMD] or this one [Git Bash],
but modern windows has another shell that is quite powerful,
and therefor is called PowerShell.
I've just started it.
Let me increase the font a little, so you could see what we are doing better.
For further work I'm going to install one really good module that is called posh-git.
It will add a current state of our git project to the command prompt.
You can go without it, but its a very usefull feature.
Heres the description of what it does and steps to install it,
which Im about to make
To install it
I run the following command: "Install-Module posh-git" for the current user
Yes, I agree to install NuGet,
I also agree to anything its going to ask me further
And module is added, lets start it.
We see an error, the system doesnt allow us to do this,
as current security settings are forbidding it.
To soften them up I will run "Set-ExecutionPolicy".
My choice means that I allow powershell to run the scripts downloaded,
if they are signed with the trusted digital signature.
Thats it, now running again. Great.
Lets create a folder for the future needs
and run a "git init" inside it,
just to see its in action
You see? Master!
this is a posh-git information
To automatically start this module whenever the powershell is started
lets run the following command [Add-PoshGitToProfile].
The basic installation is now over.
You will see it in action if you continue working with git,
and if you want to learn about the additional settings
you can find the on the authors page.
One can also find some examples there as well.
Its ok if you didnt work in a command line previously.
The basic idea is very simple,
here, on the left is a command prompt, here is a current directory,
and we type the commands on the right
You've already seen some of them,
like [cd] - change the current dir, dot [.] means - current and go to the project subfolder.
So we went from here [C:\Users\iliakan], to here [C:\Users\iliakan\project].
mkdir makes an empty directory,
the ls command will show whats inside this folder, the list of filed it contains.
In this case it contains the files, actually, but they are hidden
ls with the -hidden flag will show all of them
theres a ".git" directory
its a service directory and we will get back to it later
Lets go back to the home directory.
Home directory - its users and my name [C:\Users\iliakan],
its used so very often, that it has a special alias to go it - tilde [~].
Now I use the mv command, that can rename and move files.
With this I will move the project directory to the Desktop,
which is, actually just a "desktop" directory.
Now I will collapse all the windows
and here is my project directory
Its empty now, because the hidden files are not displayed,
if show them you will see a .git directory.
So, previously we were looking at the PowerShell setup,
but later on in a screencast
you will notice that I use another shell
Thats because I use MacOS,
and it doesnt have PowerShell
The closest analogue is Git bash,
that is being installed together with git.
There are several ways to run it
like from here or from the start menu
Or, when we were installing git we could have kept the checkbox checked
that adds the Git Bash to the context menu here
I've just started it and here it is
and my current directory is exactly the same where I've started it.
One can change colors and fonts here, in the menu and so on.
You had the following choices during the install process:
use terminal, that goes together with git or use the one that goes with windows
And we have selected the second option,
this choice affects the UI of the shell that goes together with git.
Now, just to compare and give you an idea of what is it about,
I'm going to show you how it looks if you choose the first option.
The difference is, actually quite insignificant, but there is one
Let me increase the font a little.
As you can see the colors are a little bit different
and thats basically it, the only thing that is different.
They are absolutely identical inside, same git bash,
that means that the shell that is different to PowerShell,
where the commands are completely different
although some basic commands can be used interchangebly in both.
For example to see a list of files in a directory I can use ls, same like in powershell
but to see the files, which names are starting with "."
in our case its .git I had to use -a flag, not -hidden flag
As this screencast is about git in the first place,
I will try to use the commands that are specific to one or the other shell to minimum.
Nevertheless if you work with PowerShell
and something is not working it makes sense to use gitbash,
as maybe it causes the problem
In conclusion I would like to add
that if you, like many of windows users,
are not comfortable in working with command line and prefer the UI
then most of the modern editors have extensive git integration,
so that day to day tasks can be solved with the buttons, mouse and some hotkeys.
But the command line is needed firstly to learn git
and to understand how it works
secondly - to access git features that does not have a convenient UI implemented
or have no UI implemented at all.
As git has a lot, a lot of commands.